{
  "data": [
    {
      "question": "The function of bile is to:",
      "op_1": "Digest proteins",
      "op_2": "Digest starch",
      "op_3": "Emulsify fats",
      "op_4": "Absorb water",
      "ans": "Emulsify fats"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which blood vessel has thick muscular walls to withstand high pressure?",
      "op_1": "Artery",
      "op_2": "Vein",
      "op_3": "Capillary",
      "op_4": "Venule",
      "ans": "Artery"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which form of nitrogen is absorbed by plants?",
      "op_1": "Nitrogen gas",
      "op_2": "Nitrate",
      "op_3": "Nitrite",
      "op_4": "Ammonia",
      "ans": "Nitrate"
    },
    {
      "question": "What prevents backflow of blood in veins?",
      "op_1": "Thick walls",
      "op_2": "Valves",
      "op_3": "Muscles",
      "op_4": "Arteries",
      "ans": "Valves"
    },
    {
      "question": "The main excretory product in humans is:",
      "op_1": "Ammonia",
      "op_2": "Urea",
      "op_3": "Uric acid",
      "op_4": "Carbon dioxide",
      "ans": "Urea"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which process releases carbon dioxide in living organisms?",
      "op_1": "Photosynthesis",
      "op_2": "Respiration",
      "op_3": "Transpiration",
      "op_4": "Assimilation",
      "ans": "Respiration"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a raw material for photosynthesis?",
      "op_1": "Water",
      "op_2": "Carbon dioxide",
      "op_3": "Oxygen",
      "op_4": "Chlorophyll",
      "ans": "Oxygen"
    },
    {
      "question": "The blood vessel carrying blood from intestine to liver is:",
      "op_1": "Renal vein",
      "op_2": "Hepatic portal vein",
      "op_3": "Vena cava",
      "op_4": "Aorta",
      "ans": "Hepatic portal vein"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which part of nephron is responsible for ultrafiltration?",
      "op_1": "Bowman’s capsule",
      "op_2": "Loop of Henle",
      "op_3": "Collecting duct",
      "op_4": "Tubule",
      "ans": "Bowman’s capsule"
    },
    {
      "question": "In plants, transport of food takes place through:",
      "op_1": "Xylem",
      "op_2": "Phloem",
      "op_3": "Stomata",
      "op_4": "Guard cells",
      "ans": "Phloem"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which is the site of photosynthesis in plant cells?",
      "op_1": "Mitochondria",
      "op_2": "Chloroplast",
      "op_3": "Nucleus",
      "op_4": "Ribosome",
      "ans": "Chloroplast"
    },
    {
      "question": "During respiration, glucose is broken down into:",
      "op_1": "Carbon dioxide and water",
      "op_2": "Carbon monoxide",
      "op_3": "Oxygen",
      "op_4": "Protein",
      "ans": "Carbon dioxide and water"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which organ removes excess salts and water to maintain balance in the body?",
      "op_1": "Heart",
      "op_2": "Kidney",
      "op_3": "Liver",
      "op_4": "Lungs",
      "ans": "Kidney"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which type of circulation supplies blood to the heart itself?",
      "op_1": "Systemic circulation",
      "op_2": "Pulmonary circulation",
      "op_3": "Coronary circulation",
      "op_4": "Hepatic circulation",
      "ans": "Coronary circulation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Why is diffusion insufficient for transport in multicellular organisms?",
      "op_1": "Because they have a large surface area",
      "op_2": "Because diffusion is a fast process",
      "op_3": "Because they have small volume",
      "op_4": "Because diffusion is a slow process and cannot meet high requirements",
      "ans": "Because diffusion is a slow process and cannot meet high requirements"
    }
  ]
}
